<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Adams tragedie declaring Satans malice and subtiltie, mans weaknesse and miserie, and his deliuerance from eternall captiuitie.</title>
            <author>Mabb, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 97 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17156.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4378</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">24233703</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 24233703</idno>
            <idno type="VID">27415</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06705)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 27415)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1820:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Adams tragedie declaring Satans malice and subtiltie, mans weaknesse and miserie, and his deliuerance from eternall captiuitie.</title>
                  <author>Mabb, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 100 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.W. for Thomas Downe and Ephraim Dawson, and are to be solde at their shoppe at the Inner Temple gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: I.M.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Mabb by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Title in ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Adam --  (Biblical figure)</term>
               <term>Eve --  (Biblical figure)</term>
               <term>Devil.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:27415:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27415:1"/>
            <p>ADAMS Tragedie.</p>
            <p>Declaring Satans malice and ſubtiltie, mans weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and miſerie; and his deliuerance from eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall captiuitie.</p>
            <q>Serpens Diabolus, Salus Chriſtus.</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W.W.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Downe</hi> and <hi>Ephraim Dawſon,</hi> and are to be ſolde at their ſhoppe at the inner Temple gate. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:27415:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:27415:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE AND very good Knight Sir <hi>Iohn Egerton.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He leaſt Fiſh in the Waters, the leaſt Seed in the Earth, the leaſt Flie in the Aire, and the leaſt Starre in the Firmament. (Honourable and worthie Knight) doe ſhew the glory of GOD, in their ſeuerall kinds; although not ſo great in quantity as do the Whale, the Cedar, the Eagle, and the Sunne: And the meaneſt
<pb facs="tcp:27415:3"/>
member in the body, the Foote, may performe a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruice to the Head; although not ſo lawdable &amp; worthy as the Hand. The conſideration whereof, and the happie experience of your heroicall and moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous diſpoſition, who euer haue encouraged a wel mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning minde in euery good and laudable action; maketh mee, although the meaneſt member in the Ciuill body, both venterous and hardie (in my duetifull loue) to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a litle Guift, as the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes mite, to your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian view, and Honourable accept: by whoſe good ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouement,
<pb facs="tcp:27415:3"/>
the reproch of preſumption will not be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to a well meanyng minde, when as a Chriſtian man being compared to a Tree, whoſe roote is Fayth, the body Holynes, the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Charitie, the bloſſomes Peace, and the fruite Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; is not eſteemed in the ſight of God, or good men, by the quantitie of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, but by the quality of the fruite. Wherfore, if your Honour ſhall vouchſafe by the ſunne riſing of your gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious fauour, to nouriſh a tender Grift, now yeelding a ſmall fruit vnto your taſte; and to couer it with your
<pb facs="tcp:27415:4"/>
mercifull wing, from the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and nipping ſtormes of vncharitable blaſtes: your moſt humble and deuoted protect, ſhal reſt euer bound to offer vp prayers night and day to Almighty God for your Honors eternall felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and for the proſperous and honorable continuance of your noble poſteritie in this world, and their happy enioying of the heauenly blesſinges in the world to come.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ho. in all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent duety and ſeruice, <hi>I. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:27415:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the loſſe of a Bleſsing, made <hi>Eſau</hi> weepe; and the loſſe of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, made <hi>Rachell</hi> mourne: But now behold, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Bleſsing and Children, but alſo Parents and Paradiſe lost to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.<note place="margin">Gen. 50.10.</note> It is true that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and the <hi>Egiptians</hi> made a great mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning for <hi>Iaakob;</hi> but the lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation both of <hi>Iew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> ſhould be greater, for the death of <hi>Adam;</hi> who by creation was holy and righteous, the image of God: by deputation, Lord and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunder ouer the whole World, the vicegerent of God: by bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, the Father of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind,
<pb facs="tcp:27415:5"/>
the inheritaunce of God: and by inſtitution he was placed in <hi>Eden,</hi> the Garden of God: and yet the Garden, Inheritance, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and Sanctitie, all forfeited and loſt together. Here then is the ſtratageme and inſtrument that effectes this Tragedie:<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.44.</note> 
               <hi>Satan</hi> that lyer, that murtherer from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, maligning <hi>Adam,</hi> and in <hi>Adam</hi> all mankinde, deuiſed and practiſed how to draw <hi>Adam</hi> to rebell againſt God. <hi>Adam</hi> was deceiued by the ſubtiltie of the <hi>Diuell,</hi> and he did rebell. God was diſpleaſed by the breaking of the Commaundement;<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12.</note> Sinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Death preuayled. Wherefore I intreate thee (christian Reader) which art the Child of <hi>Adam,</hi> to peruſe this Treatiſe with regard; not curiouſly excepting againſt, but graciouſly accepting what a
<pb facs="tcp:27415:5"/>
free and well meaning minde of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vnto thee, whereby thou ſhalt ſee thy Fathers and thine owne eſtate, by what meanes yee were loſt; how worthily condemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, how graciouſly redeemed, and how ioyfully receiued.<note place="margin">Luke. 10.4.</note> That ſo at all times, and in all places, thou mayſt tremble, and feare, and loue, and honour, and prayſe the Lord thy God. To whoſe infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, heauenly direction, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly protection, I heartily com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thee, for euer.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the Lord, <hi>I. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Pſal. 119 52.39,.</bibl>
               <q>I remembred thy iudgments of old, o Lord, &amp; haue been com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted: for thy iudgments are good.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:27415:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:27415:6"/>
            <head>ADAMS Tragedie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough GOD may be knowne in his glorious Workes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue mans ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe by ignoraunce for not ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing him, yet he hath reuealed his will vnto man by his Word; that man might learne to obey, and not to ſinne againſt him: And notwithſtanding that God hath ſuch care for man, yet man hath litle feare of God. As we may ſee and behold in the third
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:27415:7"/>
Chapter of <hi>Geneſis</hi> (beeing the ſubiect &amp; matter of this Booke) wherein is handled and deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, The nature of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> &amp; his queſtion vnto <hi>Eue, verſ. 1. Eues</hi> anſwere vnto it, <hi>verſ. 2.3.</hi> The <hi>Serpents</hi> replication vnto <hi>Eue, verſ. 4.5. Eues</hi> conſent to the <hi>Serpents</hi> perſwaſion, <hi>verſ. 6.</hi> Her guift vnto her Huſband of the Fruite, and his acceptance, <hi>verſ. 6.</hi> The effect of eating the Fruite, <hi>verſ. 7.</hi> The inquiſition of God after <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> for their tranſgreſsion, <hi>ver. 8.9.</hi> Their apprehenſion, <hi>verſ. 10, 11, 12.</hi> Their arreignement, <hi>ver. 13.</hi> Their anſweres, <hi>ve. 10.</hi> vnto <hi>13.</hi> Their iudgment, <hi>verſ. 14.</hi> to the <hi>20.</hi> And their expulſion out of Paradiſe, <hi>verſ. 22, 23, 24.</hi> A Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie regiſtred by the Holy Ghoſt, that it might be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:27415:7"/>
to all ages to feare to ſinne, and to learne to doe well: the wages of ſinne, being death;<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> but Life and Grace, the guift of God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <p>AS touching the nature of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> and his queſtion vnto <hi>Eue.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note> 
                  <hi>GOD</hi> (in the beginning) <hi>ſaw all that he had made, and loe, it was very good:</hi> and therefore the <hi>Serpent</hi> being a creature of God, in his firſt beeing and nature, was good: and in reaſonable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, it may ſeeme that it was a creature very pleaſing vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe it was more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile or wiſe, then any beaſt of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:27415:8"/>
the field. And therefore the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell</hi> cunningly to couer his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious and wicked intent, vſeth the <hi>Serpent</hi> as his inſtrument, to perſwade <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> vnto ſinne. Such is the craftineſſe and wilineſſe of <hi>Satan</hi> in tempting the children of God, that hee daunceth vnder a Hood, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of his face; ſeeming to be an Angell of light, when he is an Angell of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.14</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeth how to bting men vnto euerlaſting deſtruction: For, both hee, and all the euill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels that fell with him from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, (which by the ſufferance of God, doe diſpearſe and ſpread themſelues in the Ayre,<note place="margin">Reuel. 20.7, 8, 9, 10. Ephe. 2.2.</note> and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the Earth, and vnder the Earth, being continually tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the wrath of God) doe in their malice watch and deuiſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:27415:8"/>
to tempt, hurt, and afflict the Sainctes of God; and to draw them away from God, that they might be partakers of their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhmentes; ſo great is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of <hi>Satan</hi> and his members, againſt the felicitie of Gods cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen. But God in his infinite wiſedome &amp; iuſtice, doth turne the burden and bitternes of their malice vpon them ſelues: and by how much the more they ſtriue againſt God &amp; his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, by ſo much the more their curſſe is encreaſed, and God the more glorified by his Children in their preſeruation. For hee can ſlay <hi>Goliah</hi> with his owne Sword, and deſtroy Death by death,<note place="margin">1. Sam 17.51 Hoſe. 13.14. Iudg. 14.14. Gen. 3.15.</note> ſending Meate out of the Eater, and Sweetnes out of the Strong: for <hi>Satan</hi> bruſed <hi>Christ Ieſus</hi> heele; but behold, hee hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:27415:9"/>
broken the <hi>Serpents</hi> head.</p>
               <p>And in the queſtion which the <hi>Serpent</hi> made vnto <hi>Eue,</hi> two thinges are to be conſidered. Firſt, whether from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, any earthly Creature, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting Man, had the reaſon of ſpeaking; which is the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meſſenger of the Minde, diuerſly to deliuer, diſtinguiſh, deuide, &amp; apply to the outward ſenſe, and inward vnderſtanding of an other reaſonable creature, by the inſtrument of the toung, whatſoeuer the minde purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to doe, or obtaine. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whether the <hi>Serpent</hi> was the <hi>Diuell,</hi> or whether the <hi>Diuell</hi> was in the <hi>Serpent?</hi> For the firſt, it is moſt true, that no earthly Creature, excepting Man, had euer knowledge or reaſon of ſpeaking:<note place="margin">Gen. 1, 25.</note> For God, who made
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:27415:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Man in his owne image,<note place="margin">Exo. 4.11.12 Rom. 10.10. 1. Theſ. 5.11 Jam. 4.13.</note> gaue vnto Man onely a toung to ſpeake, &amp; that in three reſpects: The one, to confeſſe him to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation: The other, to bring men to the knowledge of God by edification one of another: And the laſt, to keepe mutuall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, commerce, and ciuill ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cietie amongeſt men; which God hath ordained for our helpe &amp; comfort, euen in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and earthly thinges. As for the Creatures,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.24.2.19.20.</note> God gaue them life, motion, and ſenſe, in their ſeuerall kindes, for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of Man; but neuer gaue them Diuine knowledge or reaſon, to iudge betweene good and euill; becauſe he made them for Man, and to be at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund and pleaſure: But Man, GOD made for him ſelfe, in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:27415:10"/>
whom he tooke moſt delight; and therefore gaue him a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Soule to thinke,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.7, 8.</note> ſtudie, and ſpeake of his glory; which no other creature vpon the earth can doe: And as Man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth and prayſeth God heere vpon the Earth,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.32.</note> ſo will God confeſſe him in Heauen; where he ſhall dwell with him, and his holy Angels for euer.</p>
               <p>But it may bee obiected by ſome,<note place="margin">Num. 22.28</note> that <hi>Baalams</hi> Aſſe did ſpeake: which is true. But it is to be vnderſtood, that that was miraculouſly to ſhew the power of God vnto <hi>Baalam,</hi> to ſtay him in his iourney going to <hi>Balack</hi> to curſſe the people of God. For nothing is vnpoſsible vnto God,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.26.15.31.</note> either to make the dumme to ſpeake, the halt to goe, the blinde to ſee, the dead to riſe:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:27415:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
yea, he is able of Stones &amp; Duſt,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.9.</note> to raiſe vp Children vnto <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> But from the beginning, in the nature and creation of Beaſtes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.9.</note> God gaue them a voyce onely, no ſpeach, and ſenſe, but no vnderſtanding or wiſedome: for that onely is proper vnto Man. So then it was not the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent</hi> that ſpake, but the <hi>Diuell</hi> in the <hi>Serpent:</hi> and ſo was he in the man that was poſſeſſed,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.2. Mar. 16.9 Math. 5.12.13.</note> and in <hi>Marie Magdalen,</hi> and in the heard of Swine.</p>
               <p>And further, in the queſtion of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> two other things are to bee conſidered: <hi>Satans</hi> boldneſſe to tempt, and his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie in tempting. Certaine and ſure it is, that there is no time, place, nor perſon; when, where, and whom the <hi>Diuell</hi> will not moſt boldly ſeeke to tempt and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:27415:11"/>
to ouerthrow: for as he is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trueth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.44.</note> ſo he is without ſhame.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.25.</note> He will be ſowing of Tares amongſt the good Seed, whileſt the Husbandman ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth. He will offer himſelfe to be a lying Spirit in the mouth of <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets.<note place="margin">1. Kin. 22.20.21. Iob. 1.11. Mat. 4.1.</note> He will ſtand vp to accuſe <hi>Iob:</hi> and moſt bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſay to tempt <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For the Battayle is ended in Heauen betweene <hi>Michaell</hi> and the <hi>Dragon:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reuel. 12.7, vnto 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Michaell</hi> and his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels haue preuayled, and there is ioy and ſaluation in Heauen: but the <hi>Diuell</hi> and his Angels are caſt out, and come downe vnto men vpon the Earth, with great furie and wrath, knowing that he hath but a ſhort time. His Armie is great, his Stratagems ſubtile, his Malice fierce, his Weapon death. We muſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:27415:11"/>
awake out of ſleepe,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.14.</note> and ſtand vp from the dead, and not to ſpend time, and liſten vnto, or parley with <hi>Satan,</hi> as <hi>Eue</hi> did; but ſpeedily to take the whole Armour of God vnto vs,<note place="margin">6.11.</note> and enter into fight with <hi>Satan,</hi> ſhouting and lifting vp our voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces loude and couragiouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him,<note place="margin">Ioſhu. 6.5.</note> as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did his Trumpets before the walles of <hi>Ierico;</hi> that ſo by our Fayth in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Diuell</hi> and his forces might fall, lie flat, and be troden vnder our feete for euer.</p>
               <p>And touching his ſubtiltie in tempting,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 20.9.10.</note> he is like vnto <hi>Ioab</hi> in his treacherous killing of <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa:</hi> like vnto <hi>Iaell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 4.18.</note> who in one hand caryed Milke, and in the other, a Mallet: and like vnto <hi>Iudas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.47.</note> who gaue a Kiſſe vnto <hi>Christ,</hi> ſaying; <hi>All Haile;</hi> and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:27415:12"/>
made a hiſſe vnto the <hi>Iewes,</hi> bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kning vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Come, take him; this is hee.</hi> For the <hi>Diuell</hi> neuer reuealeth himſelfe at the firſt, as he is, for feare of diſcouerie; but creepeth and windeth in, by litle and litle, into the heartes of men:<note place="margin">Math. 15.19 Ephe. 5.4. Iam. 1.15.</note> as firſt, by idle and vaine thoughtes; then by fooliſh, idle, and vaine wordes: and laſtly, he draweth them to vile and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked workes, beeing rocked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe in the cradle of Securitie: and then, <hi>Satan</hi> hauing gotten full poſſeſsion of their heartes and mindes, he diſcouereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe vnto them as he is.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5 8. Reu. 12.9.</note> To the fearefull &amp; vnbeleeuing a <hi>Lion,</hi> readie to deuoure: to the ſimple, a <hi>Serpent</hi> to deceiue:<note place="margin">9.</note> to the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell, a <hi>Dragon</hi> to ſet them on fire: to the malitious,<note place="margin">9.3.</note> a <hi>Scorpion</hi> to teach them to bite: to the proud,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:27415:12"/>
a <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 14.12, 13.</note> to teach them to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine: to the couetous,<note place="margin">Pſal. 104.26.</note> a <hi>Leuia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> to teach them to oppreſſe: to the licentious,<note place="margin">Jere. 5.8.</note> a <hi>Pampered Horſe</hi> to make them neigh after wanton fleſh: and to thoſe that be blaſphemous and reprobate, a <hi>Baſan Bull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 22.12.</note> to teach them to bellow and roare out blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and fearefull oathes againſt the Maieſtie of God.</p>
               <p>Thus doth the <hi>Diuell</hi> both ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly tempt, and openly animate man to ſinne and rebell againſt God: But to auoyde his ſnares, and eſcape his tyrannie, wee muſt continually pray vnto the Lord for ſtrength, and grace,<note place="margin">Rom. 12.12. Mat. 14.30, 31.10.16.</note> that wee may not be fearefull, but faythfull; not ignorant, but wiſe;<note place="margin">Reue. 3.16.</note> not cold and without ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall affection, but zealous to learne his law, and obey his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:27415:13"/>
will; that wee may bee able (through his power) to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande,<note place="margin">Ephe. 6, 16.</note> and quench the fierie dartes of our enemie the <hi>Diuel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>AS touching the anſwere of <hi>Eue</hi> vnto the <hi>Serpent,</hi> two things therein are to be conſidered: The <hi>Simplicitie</hi> of <hi>Eue,</hi> and her <hi>Sinceritie.</hi> Her <hi>Simplicitie,</hi> becauſe ſhe did not diſcerne not ſuſpect the <hi>Serpents</hi> ſubtiltie: For in the <hi>1. verſ.</hi> of the <hi>3.</hi> of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> you may read, that the <hi>Serpent</hi> the <hi>Diuell,</hi> did not openly ſhew his purpoſe vnto <hi>Eue,</hi> by perſwading her in plaine tearmes, You may eate of the Fruite; but made as it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:27415:13"/>
were a careleſſe queſtion vnto her, ſaying: <hi>Yea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>hath God indeed ſayd, Yee ſhall not eate of euerie Tree of the Garden?</hi> Wherein we may ſtill ſee the ſubtiltie of <hi>Satan,</hi> how he compaſſeth and ouercommeth thoſe that are ſimple and thinke no ill. For, firſt he inſinuateth and draweth <hi>Eue</hi> to make a confeſsion of God, and of his Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and afterwarde perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth her to breake the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, and to diſobey God; to th'end her puniſhment and condempnation might be the greater: For by how much the more it is for Gods glory, and mans conſolation, ſteadfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his hart to beleeue in God,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.9.</note> and boldly with his mouth to confeſſe him vnto ſaluation, &amp; neuer to deny him: By ſo much
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:27415:14"/>
the more it is to Mans ſhame and condempnation, when hee hath once beleeued God,<note place="margin">Heb. 6.4, 5, 6.</note> and confeſſed him; then after, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie him, and forſake him. And therefore wee muſt be wiſe, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as ſimple and innocent, and pray for Grace,<note place="margin">Iohn. 4.1.</note> that we may be able to iudge betweene the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and try whether they be of God or not; that ſo wee might not yeeld vnto the leaſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but ſhut our heartes, and ſtop our eares thereat; for the <hi>Diuels</hi> motions neuer tende vnto the good of Man, vnles through true obedience &amp; fayth in God, we ioyfully and conſtantly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt and ouercome them;<note place="margin">Jam. 4.7.</note> and ſo ſhall God haue the glory, and wee the victorie. For as the Thiſtle or Thorne in the filde, will not ſting or pricke vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:27415:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
we wrappe or cloſe them in our handes: no more can the queſtions or temptations of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> hurt our ſoules, vnleſſe wee are willing to harken therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and imbrace it in our hearts. And therefore wee muſt follow the example of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 39.10.</note> to flie from temptations and worldly luſtes, which fight againſt the ſoule: for they are but as a Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot to entice vs, and as a Snake to ſtinge vs vnto death.</p>
               <p>And as touching the <hi>Sinceritie</hi> of <hi>Eue,</hi> it plainely appeareth in her true anſwere vnto the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> for ſhee neither concealed her owne action, which in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſhee did performe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, in eating onely but of the permitted Fruite: neither did ſhee keepe ſecret Gods eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall Commaundement, which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:27415:15"/>
was his prohibition, that they ſhould <hi>not eate of the tree in the middeſt of the Garden.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.17.9.</note> Wherby we may note, that we muſt not conceale the trueth, but confeſſe it, euen to the moſt wicked, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing asked thereof, when as by our anſwere, God is magnified, by confeſsing of him, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his commandement which he hath willed &amp; deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. And in this <hi>Eue</hi> was to be commended, in which all other the children of God ought to follow her example. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, in the end, ſhee was more blameable, becauſe after ſhe had confeſſed God, and his commandement, yet ſhee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed God in breaking of his Commandement.<note place="margin">Mat. 16.16.</note> It was <hi>Peters</hi> caſe, he made a good confeſsion; there was his ſinceritie: but after
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:27415:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he made a wicked deniall:<note place="margin">Mat. 26.7.</note> there was his apoſtacie. It is therfore better to be conſtant &amp; end well, then in the beginning to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe well, and ende ill: for wee muſt not <hi>begin in the ſpirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and end in the fleſh.</hi> It is better to be a <hi>Conuert</hi> with <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 9.6.</note> &amp; ſo to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, then to be an <hi>Apoſtle</hi> with <hi>Iudas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.48.</note> and after to fall away for euer: But <hi>Eue</hi> &amp; <hi>Peter,</hi> as they fell away by weakneſſe and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, ſo vpon their true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and fayth in God, they were reſtored by the obedience of <hi>Christ;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 3.22.</note> which was imputed vnto them, and alſo vnto vs, in the loue of GOD the Father through him,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> from before the foundation of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:27415:16"/>
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p>AS touching the <hi>Serpentes</hi> Replication vnto <hi>Eue,</hi> two thinges therein are to be conſidered: The direct oppoſition of <hi>Satan</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods word, in ſaying, <hi>Yee ſhall not die at all.</hi> And his colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable argument to approoue his oppoſition, in theſe wordes, <hi>But God doth know, that you ſhall be as Gods.</hi> In the Oppoſition, is alſo to be conſidered two thinges; the Impudencie of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and his Malice. His Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie, that hee dares oppoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods word. His Malice, that he ſeeketh in as much as in him lieth, to diſhonour God, by falſefying of his trueth. In the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:27415:16"/>
colourable argument, is alſo to be conſidered two thinges: <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> fiction, or feigning of a feare in God, in theſe wordes: <hi>But God doth know &amp;c.</hi> And his ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of mans high felicitie, aboue their created eſtate, in theſe wordes: <hi>Yee ſhall bee as Gods, knowing good and euill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As touching the Oppoſition, <hi>Satan</hi> dealeth againſt God as a fugitiue Traytor doth againſt his Prince; who when he ſeeth that he can not hurt or annoy his Prince by open force, then he worketh by malice in ſecret places, to defame the Prince, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credite his lawes, and draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his Subiectes from their obedience. So,<note place="margin">Mat. 8.29</note> the <hi>Diuell</hi> being not able to withſtand the Lord, nor daring to appeare in his ſight, yet ſecretly diſhonoureth
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:27415:17"/>
God, ſcandalizeth or ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his word, and ſeeketh to intice and draw away man from his obedience vnto God, impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſending foorth blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies againſt God and Heauen, and deceiuing &amp; deluding men with lyes; bewitching them with ſorceries, &amp; blinding them with vanities, that they might fall with him into the pitte of euerlaſting deſtruction.</p>
               <p>And whom ſoeuer the vice of <hi>Impudencie</hi> doth poſſeſſe, let them tremble and feare, leaſt it make them, like vnto <hi>Satan,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient vnto God, and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious vnto men: For in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent mans heart, Malice lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſecretly, Blaſphemie is in his mouth, Pride appeareth in his eyes, Vnrighteouſneſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth in his handes; and he
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:27415:17"/>
walketh and vaunteth himſelfe in euery wicked and vngodly way: as did <hi>Lamech,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.23.</note> who <hi>would ſlay a man in his wound, and a young man in his hurt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as concerning <hi>Satans</hi> Malice, it hath a reſpect, &amp; eye,<note place="margin">Satans malice againſt God and man</note> to two ſeuerall perſons: God, and Man. To God, againſt his dignitie: To Man, againſt his felicitie. Hee euer enuied the one, and continually maligned the other; becauſe his pride be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his fall, could brooke no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour; &amp; his miſerie ſince his fall, maketh him repine at the proſperitie of an other. But the fruite and end of his Malice, was vtter deſtruction to him ſelfe for euer.<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.16.</note> And ſo ſhall it befall vnto all them that eyther feeke of ſelfe-will and purpoſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour God; or to hurt and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:27415:18"/>
ouertrow their breathren. And touching the colourable argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherein <hi>Satan</hi> fayneth a feare in God, how impudent was the <hi>Diuell</hi> to alleadge it, and <hi>Eue</hi> ſimple to beleeue it? that God, the Lord of Heauen and of Earth,<note place="margin">Read Iob from the 37. chap. to the 42.</note> who by his power hath made, bindeth and looſeth all thinges: by his glorie, light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, filleth, and beautifieth all thinges: by his Wiſedome or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth, guydeth, and inricheth all thinges: by his Iuſtice ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth, waigheth, and iudgeth all thinges: and by his Mercie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth, preſerueth, and ſaueth all thinges: that hee this Almighty GOD I ſay, ſhould ſtand in feare of any,<note place="margin">Read Pſal. 104. and the 107.</note> when as the Angels are his Meſſengers, the Heauens are his Throne, the Earth is his foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole, the Sea is his Seruant, all
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:27415:18"/>
Creatures waite vpon him; the bright ſhyning Sunne is his Hearauld, the Thunder is his Trumpet, the Lightning is his Dart, the Starres are his Hoaſt, the Cloudes are his Chariots, and the Night is his Tent. But woe be to <hi>Satan,</hi> for hee lyeth now trembling, and flat before the Lord; and the wicked flie from before his preſence,<note place="margin">Reuel. 6, 15.16.</note> deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to haue their habitation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Rockes, crying out vnto the Mountaines and Hilles that they would fall vpon them, and couer them and hide them, (if it were poſsible) from the ſight of God, that they might neuer come to iudgement for their ſinnes: but as they haue contemned God in their life, ſo he will condemne them in their death, neuer to be redeemed, but
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:27415:19"/>
tormented with the <hi>Diuell</hi> and his Angels, in Hell fire for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more:</p>
               <p>And as touching <hi>Satans</hi> ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or feigning of mans high Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie aboue their created eſtate, he much deceiued, and abuſed <hi>Eue:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mans eſtate before his fall.</note> For it is plaine &amp; euident, of what matter man was made of;<note place="margin">Gen. 1.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Of the Duſt:</hi> By whom he was made; <hi>by God:</hi> in what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he was made; <hi>God breathed in his face breath of life: and the Man was a liuing ſoule;</hi> that is, an Eternall creature, not ſubiect to death by Creation, but by his diſobedient action againſt God: in what place he was put;<note place="margin">verſ. 8.</note> not in the wide Field, but in a pleaſant <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> the <hi>Garden of Eden:</hi> what Companion he had;<note place="margin">verſ. 18.</note> not any creature inferiour to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but one whom God made
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:27415:19"/>
and tooke out of Man,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.21.23.</note> &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called <hi>Woman,</hi> bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, that there might be a continuall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie, and ſimphathy in perfect loue and vnitie betweene them, to their endleſſe comfortes: and ſo God called them <hi>Man &amp; Wife.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 24.</note> This was the eſtate of Man and Woman, happie and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent: But after their fall,<note place="margin">Mans eſtate after his fall.</note> their condition was changed, from peace and glory,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.7.</note> to feare and ſhame: from ioy and pleaſure,<note place="margin">16.17.19.</note> to ſorrow and labour: and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtead of comfort in each other, they greiued and accuſed one an other.<note place="margin">verſ. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> indeed in his firſt eſtate, was like a greene Oliue tree, fat and fruitfull;<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.9.</note> but when Sinne and Pride entered into his heart, hee was like a Bramble, enuious and aſpyring:<note place="margin">verſ. 15.</note>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:27415:20"/>
the Water of life did nouriſh the one, and the Fire of Gods wrath (had not Chriſt quenched it by his Blood) had conſumed the other.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Kin. 13.11 vnto ver. 25.</note> For as the man of God beleeued the olde lying Prophet, ſo <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued the old lying <hi>Serpent;</hi> for the which, they were ſlaine by a Lion, but not torne in peeces, but in mercie preſerued for a glorious reſurrection. Thus was Man happie, vnhappie, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine happie: onely made hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord.<note place="margin">2. Kin. 13.20.21.</note> For as the body of the dead man which was caſt into the Sepulchre of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> by tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the bones of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> was reuiued &amp; ſtood vpon his feete: So <hi>Adam</hi> being dead, and ſlaine by that roaring Lion <hi>Satan,</hi> hee was made aliue in <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.22</note> whom
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:27415:20"/>
by Fayth in the Promiſe he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and applyed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as his onely Sauiour,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7.</note> by whom wee haue redemption through his blood, euen the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes according to his rich grace and loue,<note place="margin">and 2.4, 5, 6.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath quickned vs, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs vp vnto eternall life. And therefore let euery one, by the example of our Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Selfe-liking dangerous.</note> beware of ſelfe-liking and flattering conceit, which is the wild-fire of <hi>Satan,</hi> to blow vs vp on hie, that we might fall downe into the bottomleſſe pit beneath:<note place="margin">Luk. 14.11.</note> for euery one that wil exalt himſelfe, ſhall be brought low; and he that humbleth him ſelfe, ſhall be exalted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:27415:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p>ANd as touching the <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Conſent to the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents</hi> Perſwaſion, in it are to be conſidered, foure principall thinges. Her Reuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution or pondering vpon the temptation. Her outward Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection of the beautie of the Fruite. Her inward Inſpection of the qualitie thereof: And her ſetled Reſolution, to take and eate thereof.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Reuolution: As in all naturall &amp; vitall things, no thing is ſodainly perfected, but there muſt be firſt, Conception, then Nutritio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then Concreſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">No man ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly vitious.</note> &amp; then Perfection: So in the Spirituall conſent of the minde
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:27415:21"/>
to acte and performe any thing, there is required, firſt; a Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then Attention, then Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, then Deliberation, then Conſent, then Action. And this courſe was obſerued by the tempter the <hi>Diuel,</hi> and by <hi>Eue</hi> the tempted: For <hi>Satan</hi> made the Motion vnto her, ſaying,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Hath God in deed ſaid, yee ſhal not eate? Eue</hi> liſtned and gaue eare, aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering: <hi>If we eate, we die.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſ. 3.</note> Hee replyed, and perſwaded:<note place="margin">4.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye ſhal not die;</hi> but if you eate,<note place="margin">5.</note> 
                  <hi>Your eyes ſhall be opened, and yee ſhall be as Gods, knowing good and euill.</hi> Herevpon ſhe deliberated; and ſo ſhee <hi>ſeeing that the Tree was good for meate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">6.</note> then ſhe Conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and Approued what was Perſwaded, and after Effected and Acted what ſhee had Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto; for ſhe <hi>Tooke of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:27415:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
fruite,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Great danger to liſten to temptations.</note> 
                  <hi>and did eate.</hi> Whereby we may ſee the readineſſe of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> to corrupt the minde of Man; and Mans ſimplicitie, to giue attention, his weakneſſe to be perſwaded, his idleneſſe to deliberate, his fooliſhneſſe to conſent, and his wickedneſſe to performe. Wherefore let euery one that is deſirous to ſerue the Lord, and obey his voyce, giue no attention to <hi>Satans</hi> motion, but ſtoppe the eare, though hee charme neuer ſo ſubtilly: For if thou wilt heare his motion, yet heare not his perſwaſion: If he will perſwade, yet keepe it not in minde to deliberate vpon it, leaſt it ouerſway thy Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and corrupt thy Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. If thou ſhouldeſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate, yet conſent not: for con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupiſcence with conſent,<note place="margin">Jam. 1.14.15</note> in the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:27415:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
end, bringeth foorth the action of ſinne, and ſinne bringeth foorth death. And therefore,<note place="margin">A ſimilitude of watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe againſt temptations.</note> as in a Towne of warre, all Portes and Paſſages muſt be ſtopped, not onely to reſiſt and keepe out the troupes and ſtrength of the Enimie, but alſo the Scoutes and Spies of the Armie: So euery Chriſtian man, who is in this world at warfare with <hi>Satan,</hi> Sinne, &amp; Death, muſt not onely giue an eye &amp; watch to the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant and groſſe Sinnes, which are like the <hi>Anakims,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 13.33.34.</note> ſtrong and tall, eaſely &amp; a farre off to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, but we muſt alſo ſtop the paſſages of <hi>Satans</hi> ſpies &amp; ſcouts; which are, idle Motions, vaine Perſwaſions, carnall Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp; fleſhly Conſent: which if we diſcerne not, and in time preuent, they will ſeaſe vpon,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:27415:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and catch vs, and lead vs away captiues vnto <hi>Satan,</hi> chayned with the ſtrong fetters of ſinne, to be ledde vnto eternall death: And therefore ſo ſoone as wee feele and perceiue in our ſelues any idle Motions, rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gods Spirit and Word, let vs not by any meanes conſult and deliberate therevpon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out calling to God, for his eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciall grace to giue vs ſtrength and iudgment, that we may be able to confute, repell, and reſiſt the ſame.</p>
               <p>And concerning <hi>Eues</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection, or beholding of the outward beautie of the Fruite, two thinges therein are to be conſidered: the Precurrencie or Forming of the outward ſenſe to like, and the Concurrencie or Conſent of the inward affection
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:27415:23"/>
to imbrace.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note> God in the finiſhing of his works, <hi>Saw all that he had made, and loe, it was very good:</hi> And in the diſpoſing of his Creatures, when he preſented them vnto man, man did ſee that they were <hi>very glorious.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 8.1.</note> And as God made the <hi>Eare</hi> an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to conueigh Fayth into the Heart,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.14, 17.</note> ſo he made the <hi>Eye</hi> an inſtrument to conueigh pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes into the Mouth.<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.3.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 11.2.</note> But as <hi>Nahaſh</hi> the <hi>Ammonite</hi> did ayme at the right eyes of the men of <hi>Iabeſh Gilead</hi> to thruſt them out, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bring a ſhame vpon <hi>Iſrael;</hi> So <hi>Satan</hi> picketh at this excellent inſtrument the Eye of man,<note place="margin">Satan aymeth at the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall part, the eye, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it.</note> to blind &amp; corrupt the ſight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to make it to diſhonor God, by conueighing an vnlawfull deſire into the heart of <hi>Eue,</hi> to bring a ſhame vpon her, and her
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:27415:24"/>
poſteritie.<note place="margin">The outward ſenſes are the vſhers vnto ſinne.</note> Wherefore the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſes are as Vſhers and forerunners to make way vnto the minde, that it might embrace and giue conſent vnto what the ſenſe and body liketh:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> For the <hi>Eye</hi> tooke delight in the beauty of the fruite, and the Heart gaue conſent, that the Hand as ſeruant to the Eye might take it; the Mouth as taſter to the Stomack, might eate it; and the Feete as Pages to the Belly, might fetch it: So that it ſeemeth, the Feete will run, the Hand will reach, the Mouth will taſte, the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke will receiue, and all what the Eye liketh.<note place="margin">The Eye a predominant ſenſe.</note> Such a predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant ſenſe and part is the Eye, that it commaundeth all the partes of the body: yea, it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth and dulleth the faculties of the Soule; for the wandering
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:27415:24"/>
of the Eye, carrieth away the Eare from hearing of the word of God; which is the foode of the Soule.<note place="margin">Deut. 7.25.26.</note> The Eye beholding the <hi>Beautie of an Idoll,</hi> perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Minde to commit Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie.<note place="margin">Mat. 5.28.</note> The Eye <hi>looking vpon a Woman,</hi> cauſeth the Heart to luſt, and to commit Adulterie. <hi>The Sonnes of God ſeeing the Daughters of Men that they were faire,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 6.<hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>tooke them Wiues of all that they liked.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioſhu. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Achan</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biloniſh garment, the Siluer and the Gold, lie glittering amongſt the ſpoyle,</hi> coueted it, and hidde them in his Tent.<note place="margin">Mat. 14.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Herod</hi> gazing vpon the <hi>dauncing Damſell,</hi> made him vow <hi>Iohn Baptists</hi> death. Therefore we ought to remember the leſſon of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour <hi>Christ,</hi> who teacheth vs, <hi>If thine Eye cauſeth thee to offend,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5.29.</note>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:27415:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <hi>plucke it out, and caſt it from thee;</hi> for,<note place="margin">Math. 6.22.23.</note> 
                  <hi>the light of the body is the eye: If the light then that is in thee be darkneſſe, how great is that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi> It is better for thee to goe with one eye into the kingdome of Heauen, then hauing two eyes, to be caſt into Hell fire for euermore. But if the eye be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vpright, then is it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared vnto <hi>Iudgement,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prou. 4.25. Pſal. 123.2. and 131.1. Iob. 31.1. and 19.20. Heb. 12.1, 2, 3.</note> to <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, Humilitie, Chaſtitie, Pitty, Fayth, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Loue.</hi> And <hi>Eue</hi> abuſing her Eye, yeelded vnto ſinne, and coueted the forbidden Fruite.</p>
               <p>And concerning <hi>Eues</hi> Inſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Conſideration of the inwarde qualitie of the Fruite. Certaine it is, after the Eye was delighted with the Beautie, and the Stomacke longed after the meate of the Fruite; then was
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:27415:25"/>
the Minde vpon Fleſhly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, and Debate perſwaded, that it was to be deſired to get knowledge and dignitie.<note place="margin">Euery ſinne will haue a colour of ſome good in it.</note> Such is the policie and ſubtiltie of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> to deceiue the Minde, to draw it to conſent and agree to ſinne, vnder colour and ſhew of ſome good, moued &amp; propoſed vnto it: And therefore the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterer continueth in his ſinne, ſaying, It is Phiſicall: the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous in his ſinne, ſaying, It is Frugall: the Ambitious in his ſinne, ſaying, It is Honourable: the Proude faſhioned in his ſinne, ſaying, It is comely: the Drunkard in his ſinne, ſaying, It is brotherly Fellowſhip: &amp; the Swearer in his ſinne, ſaying, It is Trueth. But,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Woe be vnto them that ſpeake good of euill, and euill of good; which put darknes for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:27415:26"/>
light, and light for darknes; that put bitter for ſweete, and ſweete for bitter:</hi> for ſinne, may make an excuſe to the ſinner, &amp; blind his eyes with ſome ſhew of goodneſſe in the ſinne, that hee ſhall not ſee his fault; but it can not ſo excuſe him before God, and blinde his fight, who will iudge and condemne him for his ſinne.<note place="margin">A ſimilitude againſt fleſhly and carnall defence of ſinne.</note> For as the Bird that is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the Snare, or the Fiſh in the Nette, the more they ſtriue to get foorth by their owne ſtrength, the more they are fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and entangled: So Man, when his outwarde ſenſes and partes are taken and ſnared by ſinne, the more he ſtriueth to make paſſage from ſinne by the ſtrength of reaſon, and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his owne hart, the more he is intangled in the ſnare of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:27415:26"/>
ſinne, and in danger neuer to get foorth. For thinkeſt thou, (ô fooliſh man) that thy Reaſon ſhall ouerrule and defeat Gods Law? Or ſhall thy flattering and ſmooth Interpretation of ſinne, free thee from Gods Iudgments denounced againſt ſinne? Nay, it ſhall not helpe thee: for could this haue ſerued the turne, our Parents had not been caſt out of <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> For what better co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour or excuſe to couer their ſinne, then, <hi>Deſire of knowledge?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> the onely ioy and felicitie of the Minde.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.9 vnto ver. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul</hi> had not been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued from his Kingdome; for what better colour or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, then Pitty and Mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Agag,</hi> a diſtreſſed and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue King, and <hi>Sauls</hi> pretended care to preſerue the beſt Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell for Sacrifice; What better
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:27415:27"/>
colour could it haue, then Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? and yet for all this, <hi>Sauls</hi> ſin was not done away.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.6.7</note> 
                  <hi>Vzzahs</hi> Zeale, could not excuſe his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption: nor the Simplicitie of the <hi>Man of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. king. 13.8.</note> excuſe his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience.<note place="margin">Luk. 12.18.9</note> The <hi>Rich mans</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, could not exempt his life from Graue:<note place="margin">Act. 5.1. vnto verſ. 12.</note> nor <hi>Ananias</hi> and his wiues Care, to ſaue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for their Familie, excuſe their Impietie, who lyed not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Men, but vnto God. For ſo pure, ſo iuſt, ſo holy, ſo righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſo mighty, ſo powerfull is the Law, and Word of GOD, that the breakers and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners thereof, ſhall not go vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; no, not the deare Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.18.</note> And therefore, <hi>If iudgement</hi> (for ſinne) <hi>begin at the houſe of God, where ſhall the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly appeare?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Be not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:27415:27"/>
deceiued: God is not mocked.</hi> His word is <hi>Trueth</hi> and <hi>Amen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.20.</note> for euer. <hi>Be not ouercome of euill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.21.</note> 
                  <hi>but ouercome euil with goodneſse:</hi> for, <hi>Bleſſed are they,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reue. 22.14.</note> 
                  <hi>that keepe and doe the Commandements of the Lord, that their right may be in the tree of Life, and may enter in through the gates into the holy Citie</hi> (hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Ieruſalem:<note place="margin">verſ. 15.</note>) <hi>for without ſhall be Dogges</hi> (ſuch as are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious) <hi>and enchaunters,</hi> (ſuch as are deceiuers,) <hi>and whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and murtherers, and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and whoſoeuer loueth and maketh lyes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And concerning <hi>Eues</hi> ſetled Reſolution or Determination to <hi>Take and eate</hi> the Fruite: It may be ſayd,<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.5.</note> that as <hi>Gideons</hi> Souldiers when he went againſt the <hi>Midianites,</hi> were knowne to be reſolute &amp; not feareful, by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:27415:28"/>
lapping of water with their tongues: So <hi>Eue</hi> was knowne to be reſolute and not fearefull, to breake the Commandement of God, by taking with the hand, and taſting with the mouth, of the forbidden Fruite.<note place="margin">A ſimilitude that ſinne is dead and of no force, vnles the heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</note> And as the plentifull ſtore of Weapons for Warre, pleaſure not the Captaine, without men to weare them: ſo the readineſſe of the Senſes vnto ſinne pleaſure not <hi>Satan,</hi> without the Heart to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace them. And like as the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die is dead without the Soule, ſo Sinne is dead without the Heart: for the Senſes may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, and Luſt may be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; but it is the Conſent and Reſolution of the Heart, that bringeth foorth Sinne, &amp; giueth ſtrength &amp; courage to the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body, to finiſh and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:27415:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
performe it, to <hi>bring forth death.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1.15.</note> Therefore in this reſolution of <hi>Eue,</hi> both the Captaine and the Souldiers, the ſoule &amp; the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Body did all march forward with one conſent, and reſolued without all feare, to take and eate of the fruite of the Tree:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 26.6, 7.</note> Euen as <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaj</hi> went boldly without all feare into the Hoaſt of <hi>Saul,</hi> and tooke away his Speare and Pot of water which were ſtanding by his head: for it is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, if once the Soule longeth and thirſteth for ſinne, the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the body are ſet on fire, &amp; without al feare will aduenter to ſatisfie her deſire; euen as the Seruants of <hi>Dauid</hi> when he lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for Water out of the Well of <hi>Bethlem,</hi> they preſently ranne and brake into the Hoaſt of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:27415:29"/>
                  <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and drew, and tooke, &amp; brought it vnto him. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, although the Senſes being drawne and entiſed vnto ſinne, are ſtrong allurers and flatterers of the Soule, to giue and graunt her conſent; becauſe without it they can doe nothing, no more then the Members without the Head: yet the Soule imbracing Sinne, ſhe can without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Senſes, commaunde the Body: For ſhe is (being once wicked, &amp; reſolued vnto ſinne) ſtrong and tyranous, like the <hi>Legion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mark. 5.2. vnto 14.</note> which will not ſuffer the body to reſt neither night nor day, but will diſtract, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and torment it, and all the partes thereof, vntill it obey her will, to runne headlong with her into the lake of eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:27415:29"/>Thus we ſee the Reſolution of <hi>Eue,</hi> and the cauſe thereof: her Senſes entiſing, &amp; her Soule conſenting, to take and eate of the forbidden Fruite. But let vs beware by her example, not to be ſo forward in euill; but to be onely reſolute in that which is good: and in it, to <hi>Stand faſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16.13.</note> and for it, to fight a good fight: and ſo to continue ſteadfaſt and faythfull vnto the end, that wee may be ſaued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <p>AS touching the Womans <hi>Guift</hi> to her Husbande; and his <hi>Acceptance:</hi> Two thinges therein are to be conſidered; <hi>Eues</hi> ſimple <hi>Intent,</hi> and <hi>Adams</hi> ſimple <hi>Conſent:</hi> the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:27415:30"/>
one in offering, the other in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Fruite.<note place="margin">Eues loue in true ſimplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto her husband.</note> 
                  <hi>Eue</hi> in deed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded her Husband to take and eate the Fruite, and that for loue to him; becauſe ſhee thought, that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould haue been made more happy, and not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, by it. And although her ſinne in yeelding to the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Serpent,</hi> can not be excuſed; yet in giuing it to her husband, out of the aboundance of her loue to him, ſhe can not ſo greatly be condemned: for ſhee ſo loued him, as ſhee loued her ſelfe; and therefore would not receiue a benefite by her ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone (had it been a benefite) but ſhe would make <hi>Adam</hi> her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band partaker of it. And the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell</hi> in his malice, ſought the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction both of <hi>Eue</hi> &amp; <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe they were both the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:27415:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
good creatures and image of God, and beloued of God: but he came firſt vnto <hi>Eue</hi> to tempt her, both becauſe he knew that ſhe was inferiour vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> in iudgment and knowledge, and therefore not ſo well able to reſiſt &amp; confute his temptations; as alſo becauſe <hi>Eue</hi> was moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miable &amp; louely in the heart and eyes of <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe of the ioy and comfort that hee receiued from her: and therefore the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel</hi> thought that if he could per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade <hi>Eue,</hi> ſo great was the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and loue from <hi>Eue</hi> to <hi>Adam,</hi> and from <hi>Adam</hi> to her, that it were impoſsible that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them ſhould contradict one another, in any requeſt or offer that they made, they were ſo ſimple, louing, and faythfull in each others ſight. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:27415:31"/>
vnder colour of good, how eaſily might <hi>Eue,</hi> nay <hi>Adam</hi> him ſelfe bee deceiued with euill? But neither this ſimple intent,<note place="margin">Simplicitie is no excuſe for ſinne.</note> nor ſimple conſent of our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parents, can remoue &amp; aboliſh the curſſe for their ſinne. For to euery man and woman, be they either wiſe or ſimple, learned or ignoraunt, rich or poore, young or old:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> the <hi>Wages</hi> &amp; reward <hi>of ſinne, is death.</hi> For not onely Man, but euery ſenſible Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by inſtinct of nature, haue a ſenſe of things which are good or hurtfull vnto them; for the one, they imbrace as their appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant good; and the other, they fly from, as their apparant euill. How then can Man, who is the image of God, hauing a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule, indued with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in generall, and a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:27415:31"/>
giuen vnto him in particular, be excuſed by ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie, when hee breaketh the Commaundement and Law of God; the proclamation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,<note place="margin">Exod. 19.16.</note> is declared with a <hi>ſhrill Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet,</hi> that the deafe may heare it? For,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.18.</note> 
                  <hi>The ſound thereof is gone out to the vttermoſt partes of the earth:</hi> the contentes whereof are written in great Characters, that the ſimple ſighted may run and read it: and the knowledge whereof, is as cleare as the light; for,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.105. Heb. 5.12.</note> 
                  <hi>It giueth Light</hi> and Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the Simple: and, <hi>It is Milke</hi> to the weake, &amp; Meate to the ſtrong: and therfore Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitie can be no excuſe for Sinne. For as the Law and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of God is giuen to all, without reſpect of perſons; ſo it taketh vengeance againſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:27415:32"/>
all, without reſpect of excuſes. And as the fire will burne the child,<note place="margin">A ſimilitude that all are vnder the curſſe of the Law.</note> if it fall into it, as wel as the aged, &amp; the parents which ſhould haue looked after the Childe, and not the fire is to be blamed; becauſe it keepeth the naturall working and effect wherefore it was ordayned: euen ſo the Law taketh holde vpon euery one that breaketh it, for both young and old, ignorant &amp; lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhall be iudged and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by it: But the Parentes ſhall anſwere for the ſinnes of their Children, the Maiſters for the ſinnes of their Seruantes, the Princes for the ſinnes of their People, and the Paſtors and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters for the ſinnes of their Flocke;<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.17.</note> for they are as the <hi>Lords Watchmen,</hi> to looke ouer their Family, Flocke, and People: If
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:27415:32"/>
therefore they regarde not to giue warning, nor admoniſh the wicked of their wicked wayes, that they might liue and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; yet,<note place="margin">Ezek. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>The Wicked man ſhall die in his iniquitie; but his blood will I require at thy hand,</hi> ſayth the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <p>AS touching the <hi>Effect</hi> of eating the forbidden fruite; <hi>Two</hi> thinges therein are to bee conſidered: The <hi>Miſerie</hi> of Man by <hi>Tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> and the <hi>Iustice</hi> of God by <hi>Puniſhing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To diſobey Gods Word,<note place="margin">Diſobeydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the cauſe of the loſſe of Gods loue.</note> is to disinherite our ſelues of Gods loue: But our Parentes did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey Gods word, therefore as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:27415:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
much as in them lay, they disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited themſelues of Gods loue; and to be diſinherited of Gods loue, is to be bound ouer to a perpetuall ſeparation from the comfortable preſence of God, to remaine howling in Hell with the <hi>Diuell</hi> and his Angels for euermore:<note place="margin">Rom. 6.23.</note> This is <hi>The reward of ſinne, euen eternall Death;</hi> which our Parentes purchaſed to them ſelues, and their poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, by eating the forbidden Fruite, had not God in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſpared and redeemed them in the loue of his Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sinne imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the ſoule, and practiſed by the body: both ſoule &amp; body ſhall ſuffer for it.</note> For as Sinne is firſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced by the Soule, (which is immortall) &amp; afterward practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by the body, which by ſinne is made mortall; yet at the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſurrection, the body ſhall be made immortall, to ſuffer with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:27415:33"/>
the ſoule, and that moſt iuſtly: For as it ſinned with the ſoule, ſo alſo muſt it be condemned, and ſuffer with the ſoule: and as the ſoule and body maketh one Man, ſo the condemnation of them both, maketh but one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect execution of Gods iuſtice againſt them. For as Sinne is ſweete and pleaſaunt vnto Man in his life; ſo the puniſhment of Man for Sinne, ſhall be greiuous in his death: the paines and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereof, can no more be declared,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.9.</note> then <hi>The ioyes of heauen</hi> can be expreſſed: which <hi>neither Eye hath ſeene, nor Eare hath heard, nor the Heart of man can not conceiue.</hi> I might alſo ſpeake of the puniſhmentes in this life, wherewith God doth puniſh the wicked for their ſinnes: but of this, we may read at large in
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:27415:34"/>
the <hi>28.</hi> chapter of <hi>Deutronomie:</hi> to the which I do referre you: wherein as in a perfect Mirror and Glaſſe, you may behold and ſee the miſerie of Man, euen in this life, for breaking and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying the Commaundementes of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gods iuſtice is moſt vpright, and neceſſary.</note>And touching the <hi>Iuſtice of God,</hi> in puniſhing of ſinne, it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily agreeth both with his Nature, and with his Word. By his Nature he is moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie; and therefore can not but puniſh iniquitie. By his Word he hath threatned puniſhment for ſinne, and therefore ſinners muſt looke for puniſhment; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is moſt true. For who can charge the Lord, that hee hath ſpoken, and not performed what he hath ſpoken at all times, and in all ages? Or whether
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:27415:34"/>
any <hi>Tittle</hi> of the word of God hath fayled and not taken ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,<note place="margin">Math. 5.18.</note> at his appoynted time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the workers of iniquitie, as well high as low, rich or poore?<note place="margin">and 24.35.</note> 
                  <hi>For heauen and earth ſhal paſse away: but my wordes ſhall not paſſe away,</hi> ſayeth the Lord. Are not all men,<note place="margin">All men are ſinners.</note> aſwell peaſants as Princes, proceeded from the loynes of <hi>Adam?</hi> Hee ſinned; wee as children and members of him, haue alſo ſinned with him: hee repented, and was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by beleeuing the Promiſe: but whoſoeuer, and of what eſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate ſoeuer they be, that doe not <hi>Repent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 3.2. John. 3.18.</note> and <hi>Beleeue</hi> in Ieſus Chriſt the promiſed Seede, can not be ſaued. So ſincere and pure is the Iuſtice of God,<note n="*" place="margin">There is no reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with God. Deut. 10.17. Rom. 2.11. Exod. 14.28.</note> that there is no <hi>Reſpect of perſons</hi> with him: For he <hi>Drowned</hi> and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:27415:35"/>
deſtroyed aſwell <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the King, as his meaneſt Subiect that did driue his Chariot. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 16.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> were ſwallowed vp of the earth, as the meaneſt of their Famulie. It is not the potencie, maieſtie, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, honour, riches, ſtrength, or worldly wiſedome, that can ſtop the ſentence of Gods iuſtice, or ſtay the ſtroke of Gods hand: for he is pure in his iuſtice, and will not bee ouercome with Bribes: for the round World is his, and the riches thereof: And farre dearer is innocent <hi>Lazarus</hi> in the ſight of God,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.22.23.</note> then wicked <hi>Diues,</hi> clothed in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and abounding in wealth: For,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.18.</note> 
                  <hi>The eye of the Lord is vpon them that feare him, and put their trust in his mercie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:27415:35"/>
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <p>AS touching the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> of God after <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue;</hi> therein <hi>Three</hi> things are to be conſidered. The <hi>Time</hi> of the <hi>Inquiſition:</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the <hi>Inquiſition:</hi> and the <hi>Inquiſition</hi> it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>God made <hi>Inquirie</hi> after <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> when as they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from him, and had eaten of the forbidden Fruite; as <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> did after <hi>Shimei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> king. 2.36. vnto the end of the chap.</note> when he departed from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and had broken his Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for the Lord neuer puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, but when man offendeth.<note place="margin">The cry of ſinne,</note> For our ſinnes haue Voyces &amp; Winges, to cry, and flie vp be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the throne of God, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:27415:36"/>
and iudgment, as did the ſinnes of <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 18.20.</note> They are the Herauldes of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> which proclayme warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God; and therefore he muſt come downe in the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his wrath, to deſtroy his enimies, when they would march vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt him, to plucke him from his throane, and ſit in his ſeate; to be as Gods, knowing good &amp; euill: forgetting their created eſtate, that they were but <hi>Duſt and Clay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 2.7.</note> and therefore how vnable to reſiſt their Creator; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offended, is able to <hi>Breake them in peeces like a Potters veſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 2.9.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">The fruite of ſinne, is feare and ſhame.</note> For now the Lord calleth, but <hi>Adam</hi> flyeth: the Lord examineth, but <hi>Adam</hi> trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth: <hi>Satans</hi> wordes were not ſo ſweete, but the Lords voyce
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:27415:36"/>
is as bitter. The poſſeſsion of the Fruite, diſpoſſeſſed <hi>Adam</hi> of the Garden: The hope of vaine-glorie, hath brought a heape of ſhame: and the <hi>Diuels</hi> diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled roabe of Maieſtie, is turned into a Figge leafe of Miſerie. Thus ſinne is no ſoner wrought, but God is wroth he commeth in iudgement to puniſh, and the ſinner can not flie nor hide him ſelfe from his preſence.<note place="margin">Exod. 20.5.</note> 
                  <hi>He is a iealous God;</hi> he will haue his word to be obeyed, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners and breakers thereof, ſhall die the death: for as ſinne is begotten by Pride in rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, ſo it is puniſhed by Gods iuſtice in confuſion.</p>
               <p>And touching the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of the <hi>Inquiſition:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sinne cauſeth God as a iudge to inquire af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter man.</note> It was <hi>Adams</hi> breaking of the Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God: the which God
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:27415:37"/>
gaue vnto him in two reſpects: The one, to <hi>make him to know him ſelfe, that he was a Creature,</hi> becauſe he was bound to a Law by his Creator: The other, to <hi>acknowledge the wiſedome and glory of his Creator,</hi> in looking for loue and obedience from his Creature, by performance of the Law,; the which obeying, God made to man, the promiſe of life: and in diſobeying, he threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned puniſhment by death.<note place="margin">God rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the good, and puniſheth the wicked.</note> The which courſe of loue &amp; iuſtice, in rewarding and puniſhing, the Lord hath euer kept both with Men and Angels; and will ſo do vnto the end of the world: And <hi>They that haue done good,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 25.46.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhall enter into eternall life: and they that haue done euill, into eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall death.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 7.19.20 Dan. 2.37. vnto 45.</note> The <hi>Old world</hi> had not been drowned: the <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:27415:37"/>
and great Kingdomes of the earth confounded:<note place="margin">Rom. 11.19. vnto 23. Amos. 8.11.12.</note> the <hi>Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> people of God (the <hi>Iewes</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected: the <hi>Goſpel</hi> remooued from the Eaſt vnto the Weſt: and <hi>Fire reſerued vntill the laſt day,</hi> to conſume this Earth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.7.</note> and theſe Heauens; but for the ſinne of Man. Sinne,<note place="margin">Sinne is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, and monſtrous.</note> it hath a <hi>Ieſabels</hi> face, but a <hi>Scorpions</hi> tayle: It is a Monſter in the ſight of God, begotten by an euill Spirit, and nouriſhed in rebellious Fleſh: And therefore God, the onely good and glorious Creator of all thinges,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note> who <hi>Saw all thinges that he had made, and loe, they were exceeding good;</hi> hee in the puritie of his glory, muſt purge <hi>Paradiſe</hi> of this odious monſter; and in the ſinceritie of his iuſtice, deteſt Man, which hath coupled him ſelfe with this monſter
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:27415:38"/>
Sinne, and thereby disfigured and defaced the gracious image of God in him. This was the cauſe of Gods <hi>Inquiſition</hi> after <hi>Adam:</hi> for he could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his rebellion and ſinne, and ſuffer them to goe vnpuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed-</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">An Inquiſition vpon what cauſe it is grounded.</note>And as touching the <hi>Inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> it ſelfe, it declareth by the action of the inquirie, an offence offered to the Inquiſitor: for the which, God maketh freſh purſute againſt Man: And in this <hi>Inquiſition,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">God him ſelfe alone inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth after ſinne</note> God vſeth no helpe or attendance of any of his Angels, but by him ſelfe he fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth it out; becauſe hee onely knoweth the thoughtes of men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 50.6.</note> and is iudge him ſelfe: But for the execution of his will &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whether it be for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of the good, or deſtucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:27415:38"/>
of the wicked, there he vſeth for the honour and glory of his Maieſtie,<note place="margin">Reue. 8.2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>His Angels</hi> as his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantes &amp; Miniſters, to performe the ſame; and that alſo by his eſpeciall leaue and commiſsion, and not otherwiſe:<note place="margin">Without Gods eſpeciall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, the Angels neither heare the words, nor ſee the workes of men.</note> For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this eſpeciall Commiſsion, they neither ſee nor heare the wordes nor actions of men vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the earth; but onely attende about the Lordes Throne in Heauen, continually worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping him, and prayſing him, and reioycing onely in him for euer; whoſe loue and glory, taketh away from them all thought of other inferiour things, or of any perſons vpon the earth. And therefore ſeeing God him ſelfe is the <hi>Inquiſitor</hi> and finder out of ſinne, what manner of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought we to be in holines,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:27415:39"/>
and innocencie of life: for his <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Eares,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 23.24, 25.</note> doe beholde and heare a farre off. His know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is infinite, his power vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable, his preſence fearefull, his voyce terrible, his ſentence death, againſt all impenitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, euen eternall death, to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer and continue <hi>In that Lake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reue. 20.10.</note> 
                  <hi>which burneth with fire &amp; brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone for euermore.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <p>AS touching the <hi>Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion</hi> of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> to anſwere for their fault, <hi>Two</hi> thinges therein are to be conſidered: The <hi>Power of God,</hi> to apprehend: &amp; the <hi>Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Man,</hi> to reſiſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:27415:39"/>If ſo God ſhould enquire and know all things that Man doth, and yet not able to apprehende Man for his fault, what care of obedience, or what feare would Man haue of God? Nay, what blaſphemies, what rowtes and rebellion (as I may ſo ſpeake) would he not commit againſt God? For then Man would heape ſinne vpon ſinne,<note place="margin">The ſcornfull and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thought of the wicked againſt God.</note> and ſay in his heart; Tuſh, although God doth know my actions, and wicked courſe, and the thoughtes of my heart, yet hee is not able to attach and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende mee for it; and therefore I am ſtill at libertie, and falſe: I weigh not, and reſpect him no more, then <hi>Shemei</hi> did <hi>Dauid;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.5.6.</note> for his force is weake, and his hand vnable to take hold vpon mee. Thus the wicked would
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:27415:40"/>
ſay within them ſelues: nay more, they would conclude and affirme, ſaying; God indeed threatneth much, but hee can performe little. And it is true, if ſo God were not able to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the offendour for ſinne, aſwell as to inquire and finde out ſinne, the wicked might ruf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finelike thus triumph againſt God. But Almightie GOD, the Lord of Lordes, and King of Kinges,<note place="margin">Pſal. 2.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Which ſitteth in Heauen, ſhall laugh them to ſcorne, and haue them in deriſion:</hi> their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction ſhall come ſodainely, and none ſhall be able to deliuer them out of his hand.<note place="margin">Gods power to apprehend ſinners. <hi>Gen. 4.9, 10.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> hid him ſelfe, but he was found. <hi>Cain</hi> would haue concealed his brothers blood, but it was kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen.<note place="margin">Ioſhu. 7.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Achan</hi> priuily conueyed the Garment, the Siluer, and the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:27415:40"/>
Gold into his Tent, but he was diſcouered by the lot.<note place="margin">Ioſhu. 10.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The fiue Kinges that fledde before Ioſhua,</hi> were eſpied, and brought out of the Caue.<note place="margin">Act. 5.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> diſſembled, but they were ſlaine. No ſinne ſo cloſe, no place ſo ſecret, but God can finde it out, and apprehende the offendour for his fault:<note place="margin">God can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by ſmall meanes, and diuers wayes.</note> And the Lordes meanes and inſtrumentes are both many, and verie eaſie, whereby he can ouerthrow his enimies, to their vtter ſhame and confuſion: for his Finger is ſtronger then their Loynes; and his meaneſt Seruantes, able to deſtroy the greateſt Princes: <hi>One Angell can kill a hundred foureſcore and fiue thouſand Aſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, in a night. One litle Stone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. kin. 19.35.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.50</note> can ſtrike <hi>Goliah</hi> to the ground.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 18.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>A Bough</hi> can ſtay and hang vp
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:27415:41"/>
                  <hi>Abſalon</hi> by the Haire, and <hi>ſmall litle Wormes</hi> can eate vp <hi>Herod</hi> to the bones.<note place="margin">Act. 12 23.</note> What ſhall I ſpeake more of Gods power to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend offendours, dayly experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth vs, that ſinne eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth not vnpuniſhed? for, doth not the ſword of Gods Iuſtice, continually cut off Traytors, Theeues, and Murtherers? Doth not the power of Gods Curſſe, impoueriſh Drunkards, Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and Whoremongers? Doth not the plague of his hand ſend Diſeaſes, Rottenneſſe, and Burninges into the bones and bowels of Harlots, &amp; licentious Wantons?<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.35, 36. &amp; 9.6.</note> Is not the <hi>Name of the vngodly</hi> (after their death) quickly forgotten, and their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall periſheth with them? Doe not their <hi>riches take them winges,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pro. 23 5.</note> and ſpeedily flie away,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:27415:41"/>
                  <hi>and loe their place</hi> is no where to be found: <hi>This their way,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.36.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 49.13.</note> vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth their fooliſhneſſe; for the way of peace and godlines, they haue not knowne:<note place="margin">Iere. 17.11.</note> 
                  <hi>They haue ſpunne the Spiders webbe:</hi> And,<note place="margin">Math. 7.26.</note> 
                  <hi>Built their houſe vpon the Sand.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as touching the <hi>Weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> of man to reſiſt Gods power; How can Man, being a creature,<note place="margin">Man not able to reſiſt God.</note> be able to reſiſt and withſtande his Creator? and being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of ſinne, and ſubiect vnto death, How is he able to reſiſt the Iudge, who hath both ſeene his ſinne, and apprehended him to bring him vnto iudgement, that he might receaue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of ſinne, which is death; from the which, none that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, can flie or eſcape?<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.48.</note> 
                  <hi>For what man liueth, &amp; ſhall not ſee death?</hi> or, <hi>ſhall any deliuer his ſoule from
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:27415:42"/>
the hand of the Graue?</hi> Therefore if we can not reſiſt Gods Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, or Meſſenger to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende vs: how much leſſe are we able to reſiſt God,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.1.</note> the <hi>Iudge both of quicke and dead?</hi> Againe, let vs further conſider mans ſtrength, and he is but weaknes it ſelfe, reſpecting either the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward partes of his body, or the inward partes of his minde: for in his birth, his feete are not able to beare him:<note place="margin">1. kin. 12.10.</note> 
                  <hi>In his youth</hi> he hath no wiſedome to direct him: in his mans eſtate, and in his greateſt ſtrength,<note place="margin">Eſa. 46.6. vnto 9.</note> 
                  <hi>He is but a Flower,</hi> growing, floriſhing, and withered in a day.<note place="margin">2. Tim. <hi>2.</hi>22.</note> His <hi>Luſtes</hi> are vnbridled, his Affections infected, his Actions peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, his Body and Soule by <hi>Satan</hi> ouercome and ſubdued.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Poore wretch,</hi> and miſerable man, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:27415:42"/>
thou art; Is thy ſight and light, that is in thee, ſo dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened? and art thou become ſo blinde, that with the Flie in the night, thou wilt flutter and fall into thine owne deſtruction? Doeſt thou thinke thy ſelfe ſo ſtrong,<note place="margin">Gods power and might.</note> that thou canſt either wreſtle with, or reſiſt thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,<note place="margin">Reue. 6.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſe eyes</hi> are like a burning flame, that his enimies dare not behold him?<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Whoſe armes</hi> doe draw a Bow of Steele, to ſhoote out ſharpe and deadly Arrowes to pierce the heart of thoſe that hate him:<note place="margin">Reue. 1.15.</note> and whoſe <hi>Feete are as Braſſe,</hi> ſtrong to cruſh the whole nations of the earth in peeces, that ſhal ariſe vp againſt him. If thou flyeſt from him, he is <hi>Swifter then the Winde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 104.3.</note> to ouertake thee, if thou reſiſt him:<note place="margin">and 58.9.</note> as the <hi>Raw fleſh</hi> before the pottes
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:27415:43"/>
feele the fire of Thornes: ſo will he carry thee away in the whirlewind of his wrath. And then ſhall it be ſayd of thee, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 52.7.</note> 
                  <hi>that tooke not God for his ſtrength, but trusted in the multitude of his Riches, and put his confidence in his malice;</hi> and thought to flie and eſcape from the preſence of the Lord: But alas how was he deceiued? his portion is with the Wicked, and his ſinne ſhall neuer be done away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <p>AS touching the <hi>Arraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Two thinges there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are to be conſidered: The <hi>Perſon of the Iudge:</hi> and, the <hi>Priſoners at the Barre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:27415:43"/>The <hi>Iudge</hi> is, <hi>The Lord GOD;</hi> whoſe wiſedome, equitie, and order, in proceeding to tryall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Priſoners, is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued: And firſt concerning the <hi>Perſon of the Iudge.</hi> It is,<note place="margin">The dignitie of God.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord God:</hi> not a Lord, which hath his authoritie from an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but he is the <hi>Lord God</hi> of all thinges: <hi>For of him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.36.</note> 
                  <hi>and through him, and for him, are all thinges: to him therefore be glory for euer and euer, Amen:</hi> as ſayth the Apoſtle. And as he is the <hi>Lord,</hi> ſo he gouerneth all thinges, and iudgeth all men. And as he is <hi>God,</hi> ſo he hath created all things, and reſtored all things:<note place="margin">John. 1.1.</note> For he is that <hi>Eternall word,</hi> by which all things were made:<note place="margin">4.</note> that <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall light,</hi> by which all thinges are comforted:<note place="margin">and 14.6.</note> and that <hi>Eternall life,</hi> by which all thinges are
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:27415:44"/>
continued: And therefore for to ſay that he is the <hi>Lord,</hi> and not <hi>God;</hi> that were to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his wiſedome &amp; power in creating: and to ſay that he were <hi>God,</hi> and not the <hi>Lord;</hi> that were to take away his Maieſtie, Iuſtice, and Dignitie; admitting that he had power to create, but not able to rule, or gouerne that which he had created.<note place="margin">Satans ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to abridge and leſſen the dignity of God.</note> And that was the blaſphemie and ſubtiltie of <hi>Satan,</hi> to perſwade <hi>Eue,</hi> that although <hi>God</hi> had created them, and all thinges; yet he was not abſolute <hi>Lord</hi> ouer them, but that they, whether he would or no, might be partners and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his glorie with him: which to beleeue or thinke, is a moſt greiuous ſinne; yet to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it, is the ſinne of ſinnes, euen <hi>Lucifers</hi> ſinne. But <hi>GOD</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:27415:44"/>
in his iealouſie and iuſtice, with the breath of his noſtrils, and <hi>Power of his word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 18.6.</note> is able to caſt his Enimies downe headlong, and bring them to confuſion: for he hath Fire from Heauen to conſume them,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 10.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Hayleſtones</hi> to braine them, Peſtilence to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure them, the Sword to kill them, Famine to deſtroy them, <hi>Beaſtes to teare</hi> them,<note place="margin">2. kin. 6.25.</note> the Sea to drowne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Earth to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, Hell to receaue them, <hi>Paines</hi> to torment them,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.23.24.</note> Darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to incloſe them, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Condemnation to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them <hi>in that Lake</hi> which burneth with fire &amp; brimſtone for euer more.<note place="margin">Reul. 20.10.</note> And therfore <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> in tempting, &amp; our parents by attempting ſoueraignetie with <hi>God,</hi> denied him to be the <hi>Lord,</hi> although they confeſſed him to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:27415:45"/>
be <hi>God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">To confeſſe God wholly, not in part.</note> Whereby we are to learne to beware, that we doe not confeſſe God in part, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie him in part; which the <hi>Diuel</hi> did: but to hold faſt the analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of our Fayth, and euer with a pure heart to confeſſe <hi>GOD</hi> to be the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Lord God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Adam &amp; Eues arraignement.</note>And concerning the order and equitie of God in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignement,<note place="margin">Gen. 2.8. vnto verſ. 19.</note> he proceedeth firſt againſt <hi>Adam;</hi> becauſe he was created before <hi>Eue,</hi> and to him was giuen the poſſeſsion of the Garden, and the precept &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement touching the fruite, before <hi>Eue</hi> was formed &amp; made. Then next he calleth <hi>Eue,</hi> beeing bone of <hi>Adams</hi> bone, and fleſh of his fleſh, inferiour vnto him in order of nature, though firſt before him in degree of ſinne: and yet the order of the arraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:27415:45"/>
is iuſt, though <hi>Adam</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after <hi>Eue:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.9.</note> for although <hi>Cain</hi> was not his <hi>Brothers keeper;</hi> yet the <hi>Husband is the Wiues head,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.23.</note> and ought to be her <hi>Inſtructor</hi> in all the commaundementes of God,<note place="margin">The Husbands care which he ought to haue ouer his wife.</note> that ſhe might liue in his feare, &amp; be obedient vnto him: For as no reaſonable man will hurt his owne fleſh; ſo no godly man ought (through his negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence) to ſuffer his owne fleſh to ſinne, but ſtill to haue an eye and care for her preſeruation, as much as in him lyeth. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, God ſpeaketh vnto the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> as being the <hi>Diuels</hi> inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto ſinne, and maketh no further expoſtulation with him, becauſe the <hi>Diuel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Diuel was a conuict and reprobate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Adams fall.</note> who was in the <hi>Serpent,</hi> was a conuict, and condemned creature before, &amp; attainted before Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:27415:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſeate in heauen, and caſt downe from thence with the reſt of the diſobedient Angels; and therefore he commeth to no new arraignement:<note place="margin">The Serpent being the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of ſinne, is puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> but the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the creature being an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument which the <hi>Diuel</hi> vſed to draw our Parents vnto ſinne, is accurſed: which ſheweth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that not onely the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and conſenters vnto ſinne, but the dumme creatures alſo, which are meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes made by the wicked, for the inticement vnto ſinne, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed before the ſight of God; ſo holy, ſo iuſt and righteous is the Lord:<note place="margin">Deut. 28.17.18.</note> and therfore the <hi>Earth, &amp; creatures thereof are accurſed,</hi> for Mans ſake, when as by the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of <hi>Satan,</hi> Man is allured by the pleaſures thereof, to loue &amp; imbrace the world more then
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:27415:46"/>
God: And ſo in the iuſtice of God, the glorious Houſes, and ſtately dwellinges of the mighty vpon the earth, are accurſed, and <hi>made deſolate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.13.</note> for the ſinnes of the owners and buylders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, who haue rayſed vp the Walles by Oppreſsion, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Morter with Blood, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orned them with Vanitie, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed them with Pride,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.11.</note> and <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them</hi> (and their lands) <hi>by their owne names,</hi> that they might be as Gods, to liue for euer: But behold, as <hi>Adam</hi> was caſt out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> ſo are they out of their dwellinges;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>verſe</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>They lie like Sheepe in Graue, and Death deuoureth them,</hi> and their name is periſhed from of the earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:27415:47"/>
               <head>SECT. 10.</head>
               <p>AS touching their anſwers. <hi>Adams</hi> Indictment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Two partes: the <hi>Offence committed;</hi> and the <hi>Flying vpon the offence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Adams plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment.</note>Hee confeſſeth it, and would auoyde it, by way of extenuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in alleadging the principall cauſe to be the Woman. And as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his <hi>Flight,</hi> he doth alſo extenuat it by the preſence of God in following him; for he ſayth, he was afrayd, and that in two reſpectes: the one becauſe he <hi>heard Gods fearefull voyce:</hi> the other, becauſe he <hi>Saw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be naked:</hi> whereas vpon the committing of the ſinne, he feared neither the preſence of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:27415:47"/>
God, nor his owne miſerie to come, for he thought to haue been equall with God.<note place="margin">Satans ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to couer ſinne.</note> It is the ſubtiltie of <hi>Satan</hi> in drawing men forward to ſinne, to hide the hooke of Miſerie, vnder the bayte of flattering felicitie, their eyes being blinded, not to ſee the one; and their handes and feete too ſwift and forwarde to runne, and reach vnto the other. <hi>Gehazi</hi> got Money and Appar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of <hi>Naaman:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. king. 5.21.22.</note> but it infected him with Leproſie. <hi>Adam</hi> eate the Apple; but it poyſoned him euen vnto death, had not <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> his, and our heauenly Phiſition, purged him from his ſinne, which is the venome, and mother and ſting of death.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.5.6. <hi>Eues her plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>Eue</hi> in her anſwere, followeth her husbands preſident, pleading as he did; confeſsing, and auoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:27415:48"/>
the offence alleadged in her indictment, affirming the <hi>Serpent</hi> to be the cauſe of her of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. Such is the courſe and practiſe of <hi>Satan</hi> in his malice towardes man, that when man hath offended, he hardneth and ſhutteth vp his heart from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,<note place="margin">Offenders will excuſe, but not confeſſe their fault.</note> making him bold and impudent to excuſe his fault, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by poſting it ouer vnto ſome other, or dawbing and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering it with vntempered mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, falſhood, &amp; vntrueth; think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to blinde the eyes of God their Iudge: But they are deceiued; for nothing is hidde from his ſight;<note place="margin">Pſal. 7.9.</note> he <hi>Searcheth the heartes and the reynes,</hi> and the night is as cleare as the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him:<note place="margin">and pſa. 139.1. vnto. 18.</note> He <hi>knoweth mans go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing foorth, and his comming in;</hi> their wordes and their workes
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:27415:48"/>
are regiſtred before him: yea he is in the cloſets and priuie cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of men, to heare their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and to ſee their wayes: So that when they ſhall come vnto iudgement before him, the Booke of their offences ſhall be opened and read vnto them; their Conſciences ſhall tremble, their Heartes ſhall melt, &amp; they ſhall not be able to anſwere one ſinne of a thouſand.<note place="margin">In temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to thinke vpon God, is the preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſinne.</note> Therefore in the committing of ſinne, if men would but remember who ſeeth them, it would be a curbe and bridle to bring them backe: or if after the ſinne committed, they would remember who ſhall iudge them, it would be a meanes to make them humble them ſelues before the throne of God, &amp; to confeſſe their ſinnes, and craue pardone for the ſame
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:27415:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
through the merites of <hi>Ieſus Christ;</hi> who is a Sauiour vnto all them that put their truſt in him.<note place="margin">Equiuocate lying &amp; ſhif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, is moſt abhominable before God.</note> For all coulorable ſhiftes and lyes, and ſubtile equiuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, highly offendeth God, and maketh the ſinne double, and more haynous in his ſight. It had been better for our Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> plainely to haue confeſſed and acknowledged their diſobedience, then to haue poſted it, and ſhouelled it from one to another: for the <hi>Diuels</hi> ſubtiltie and malice, could not excuſe their ſinne &amp; wickednes: for as he is the roote of ſinne, ſo we are his branches, if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine &amp; continue in ſinne; and therefore of our ſelues being <hi>vnfruitfull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 2.10.</note> dead, and withered, we are worthy to be cut downe and caſt into the fire of Gods
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:27415:49"/>
eternall and moſt heauie wrath, becauſe we haue rebelled againſt him, &amp; haue not harkened vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his voyce, to bring foorth fruite worthy of amendement of life.<note place="margin">The Serpent is ſilent, and pleades not at all.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And as touching the <hi>Serpent,</hi> or the <hi>Diuell</hi> in the <hi>Serpent,</hi> he maketh no anſwere at all vnto God; neither had he any cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour to excuſe his fault by any meanes, or to lay it vpon any perſon: for he is the Author of ſinne, &amp; the Father of lyes; and therefore he is conuicted by his ſilence, and ſtandeth mute and dumme, trembling &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king before the preſence and throne of Almightie God, who is a moſt iuſt Iudge, and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord, vnto all thoſe that hate him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:27415:50"/>
               <head>SECT. <hi>11.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS touching their <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> it is ſeuerall and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the courſe that God obſerued in their <hi>Arraignement:</hi> for he firſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth ſentence againſt the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent;</hi> becauſe he was the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall actor to perſwade to ſinne: Then againſt <hi>Eue;</hi> becauſe ſhe firſt conſented to ſinne: Laſtly, againſt <hi>Adam;</hi> becauſe he agreed to his wiues perſwaſion to ſinne.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>Iudgement</hi> of the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> are to be conſidered three thinges: his exceeding Miſerie; <hi>Thou art curſed aboue all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:</hi> his Malice to Chriſt; for <hi>Enmitie ſhal be betweene thee and the Woman, betweene thy ſeede
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:27415:50"/>
and her ſeede:</hi> his Weakenes to reſiſt Chriſt; <hi>Thou ſhalt bruſe his heele, but be ſhall breake thy head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the firſt, we ſee what is the rewarde of ſinne: a Curſſe. In the ſecond,<note place="margin">Satan is enimy to God and man.</note> wee muſt conſider that <hi>Satan</hi> is Enimie to God and vs; and therefore wee muſt be Enimies vnto him: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we can not be friendes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our ſelues, nor vnto God, when we ſhall make peace, and be at league with Gods enimies. In the third, we ſee a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Victorie promiſed, which Chriſt hath gotten for vs, and his mercy in ſauing vs; who if <hi>Satan</hi> could haue preuayled, ſhould neuer haue been reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto life, but condempned vnto death for euermore.<note place="margin">Adams &amp; Eues iudgment from God is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull.</note> And the Iudgement of <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; <hi>Eue,</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:27415:51"/>
(in the loue of Chriſt) is moſt mercifull and gracious; for it is but temporall, not eternall death: And as in the pride of their heartes they forgate God, &amp; committed ſinne: ſo by their paine and miſerie in this world, they ſhall remember God, and it ſhall be a meanes to keepe them from ſinne, that they may haue ioy and peace for euermore in the world to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 12.</head>
               <p>AS touching their <hi>Expulſion</hi> out of <hi>Paradiſe:</hi> in it there are to be conſidered two things: The <hi>Care</hi> which God had of <hi>Adam:</hi> And, his <hi>Milde reprehenſion</hi> of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:27415:51"/>His <hi>Care:</hi> hee made them Coates, &amp; clothed them. <hi>Satan</hi> dealt with our Parents,<note place="margin">A ſimilitude of Satans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to God, and malice to man. 2. <hi>Sam. 10.3.4.</hi>
                  </note> as <hi>Hanun</hi> King of the <hi>Ammonits</hi> did with <hi>Dauids</hi> ſeruantes, who in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and hatred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, ſhaued off the halfe of their Beard, and cut off their Garmentes in the middle, euen to their buttocks, and ſent them away. So the <hi>Diuel,</hi> in contempt of God, and malice to Man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed how to ſhaue off with the knife of Sinne, from the heartes of our Parentes; not the halfe, but the whole ornament and beautie of grace: and to cut off not onely their Garmentes of Innocencie and Righteouſneſſe in the middle, but wholly to ſpoyle and to robbe them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to leaue them all naked, and aſhamed in the ſight of God
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:27415:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and Angels:<note place="margin">Adams ſhame.</note> Which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, and alſo perceiuing <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to be exceedingly aſhamed, by hiding himſelfe in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, as bewayling his ſinne, in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying of his gracious God and Lord; and blaming his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſo to be beceiued, deluded, &amp; ſpoyled by <hi>Satan:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gods pittie.</note> God, as a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, pittied <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; in his loue, &amp; promiſe in his ſonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> comforted the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man by fayth, &amp; hope: and renewed the outward man, by Sanctification, &amp; Preſeruation. And as the Seruaunts of <hi>Dauid</hi> were appoynted to tarry in <hi>Ieri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> vntill their Beardes were growen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1. Sam. 10.5.</hi> A ſimilitude of mans corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in earth, and of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to heauen.</note> and then to come vnto the Kinges Court at <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> ſo God hath appoynted <hi>Adam,</hi> and all fleſh the ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> to dwell vpon the earth, and to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:27415:52"/>
reſt in the Graue, vntill their mortalitie ſhall put on immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, and then to come vnto the heauenly Court of God in his holy and celeſtiall <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> there to remaine &amp; dwell with him for euer. And alſo,<note place="margin">Gods reuenge againſt Satan, for his malice to man.</note> as <hi>Dauid</hi> reuenged himſelfe of <hi>Hanun</hi> for the diſhonour offered vnto his Seruaunts, ſo God hath reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himſelfe vpon <hi>Satan</hi> for his malice vnto <hi>Adam.</hi> O the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe, and great mercy of God, thus to regarde and to take pittie vpon man, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and to preſerue him both in body and ſoule:<note place="margin">A good thing to remember our miſerie &amp; nakednes.</note> And therefore when wee feele the inwarde grace of Gods ſpirit working ſorrow in our heartes for ſinne, then let vs remember the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſoules, which once were robbed and ſpoyled by
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:27415:53"/>
                  <hi>Satan,</hi> that wicked and enuious <hi>Serpent.</hi> And when we put on our Cloathes to couer our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes, then let vs alſo remember that they are but as vayles and ſhadowes, to hide away our ſhame, being ſpotted with ſinne; and to ſheild and defende our corrupt &amp; weake bodyes from heate and cold, which are dayly ſubiect to ſickneſſe, and vnto death, by reaſon of our ſinne.</p>
               <p>And as concerning the <hi>Milde reprehenſion</hi> of God to <hi>Adam,</hi> although it may ſeeme <hi>ironicall,</hi> and in ſome ſort ſpoken by way of diſgrace, yet it is moſt milde, in reſpect of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne; who deſerued no fauour, to heare Gods mercifull voyce, ſparing, and not deſtroying him in the fiercenes of his wrath.<note place="margin">Gods loue to Adam.</note> But God here ſheweth his loue to <hi>Adam,</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:27415:53"/>
as <hi>Dauid</hi> did vnto <hi>Abſalon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 14.21.</note> for he pardoned his diſobedient Sonne, who returned home from <hi>Geſhur</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> but he muſt turne into his <hi>owne Houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">verſe 24.</note> and not ſee the King his fathers face, vntill he be called: So God pardoneth <hi>Adam,</hi> and he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the bondage of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi> and admitted into the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Sonnes of God: but he muſt turne into his owne Houſe, being <hi>Earth and Duſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> and not ſee the glorious face of God his mercifull Father in <hi>Paradiſe</hi> with theſe eyes, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he be called: which ſhall be in the day of the Reſurrection, when God will receiue his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with the kiſſes of his loue.</p>
               <p>But ſome peraduenture will ſay: Hath <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned,<note place="margin">An obiection to Gods iuſtice who did not deſtroy Adam for his ſinne.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued death, &amp; now doth God
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:27415:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
pardone and pittie him? how can this ſtand in the courſe of Gods iuſtice, when as at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie of his Commandement, he threatned death vnto <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaying: <hi>In the day that thou eatest thereof, thou ſhalt die the death?</hi> To aunſwere this Obiection;<note place="margin">The aunſwere to the obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> The Iuſtice of God is perfectly ſatisfied according to his word: for as Man ſinned, ſo Man for his ſinne had the ſentence and iudgement of death: but the execution of death for ſinne, was ſpared in <hi>Adam,</hi> and layde vpon <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 53.10. Ephe. 5.2.</note> who was made <hi>an Offering</hi> for ſinne, and appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God him ſelfe, before the foundation of the world, euen for all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that put their truſt in him: ſo that the iuſtice of God taketh effect in man; but <hi>Chrst,</hi> perfect God &amp; perfect man, hath
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:27415:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ouercome death, although his humanity for a time, was ſeaſed vpon, and kept in the graue by death, to ſatisfie the ſentence of his Fathers iuſtice, pronounced againſt <hi>Adam,</hi> yet by his Deitie he <hi>raiſed vp</hi> his Humanity from death,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.20 Joh. 17.4.5.</note> and <hi>glorified</hi> it with Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie in heauen; and he wil alſo glorifie all the faythfull that truſt in him,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.5. Gal. 4.6.</note> being <hi>ingrafted</hi> into his body, &amp; <hi>Sanctified</hi> by his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, whereby they cry <hi>Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gods proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent care ouer Adam euen in this world.</note> And notwithſtanding that <hi>Adam</hi> was caſt out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> (wherby he had a dayly &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual feeling of his miſerie, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by his ſinne) yet God left him not forlorne, but by his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious prouidence, &amp; louing eye, which he had ouer him, he kept him ſafe not onely from the rage and furie of cruell beaſtes,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:27415:55"/>
which became rebellious vnto <hi>Adam;</hi> but alſo from the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of that <hi>roaring Lion</hi> Satan,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8.</note> which gaped and euer looked for the eternall fall and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Adam.</hi> And God alſo bleſſed his labour, that the Earth thereby ſhould bring foorth fruite &amp; meate vnto him, for the preſeruation of this life: and likewiſe he continued the loue betweene <hi>Adam</hi> and his wife, that neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould take exception one againſt the other for their eiection and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting out of <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> but rather make much of, and comfort one another in the time of their pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage and miſerie of this world:<note place="margin">The mutuall loue which ſhould he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and wife</note> Which teacheth vs, that man and wife ſhould neuer fall out, or be offended with each other for the loſſes of the riches
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:27415:55"/>
and poſſesſions of this world, when as our Parentes twitted not each other in the teeth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they loſt the poſſeſsion of that ioyfull <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> O happie man,<note place="margin">The happy tranſlation of man to a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly paradiſe</note> who hath ſo mercifull a God, that ſinning, yet thou art pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: being loſt, art found: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, yet receiued: dead, yet lyueth: and liuing, ſhalt be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with him, not in the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but in the heauenly <hi>Paradiſe</hi> for euermore.<note place="margin">The glory of heauen.</note> The glory where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is infinite; for the riches there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are without meaſure: there is plentie without want, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort without griefe, light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out darkeneſſe, life without death:<note place="margin">The ioy of Gods preſence with his ſaincte.</note> Gods preſence is as a bright ſhining Temple in the middeſt thereof; before whoſe throne, doe ſtand the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and Sainctes, whoſe eyes are
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:27415:56"/>
neuer ſatisfied with beholding him, their eares neuer glutted with hearing him, their tongues neuer ſilent from prayſing him, their handes neuer wearie with lifting vp vnto him, their hearts neuer filled with the ſweetnes of his loue, and their feete neuer tyred with walking in his wayes.<note place="margin">Reu. 22.1.2.</note> There is the <hi>Water of Life,</hi> euer running: the <hi>Tree of life,</hi> euer growing, and the fruite of <hi>Loue and peace,</hi> neuer fading: To which place, and <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> God of his infinite mercy, bring vs, for Chriſt Ieſus ſake, our onely Lord and Sauiour. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:27415:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
